Winstead, Ralph D. Papers 5473
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Ralph D. Winstead Papers
1927-1957
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Winstead, Ralph D.
5473
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Manuscripts (documents), records (documents).
Papers include research data and reports for the National Recovery Administration; reports Winstead made while a field investigator for the U.S. Senate Civil Liberties Committee regarding alleged acts of espionage against unions by employers; documents relating to the 1949 National Labor Relations Board staff hearing examiners controversy; and records relating to the Shipbuilders Stabilization Committee and to the Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America.
3833925
Biographical / Historical
Ralph D. Winstead was a statistician and technical editor in the field of construction methods data, materials cost and price, and construction costs.
Winstead was a technical editor, government employee, and union official. His early career was in the construction industry in the state of Washington and in British Columbia. In 1922, he became associate editor of the F.W. Dodge Corporation trade publication, the AMERICAN CONTRACTOR. He became editor of the publication in 1927 only to leave in 1929 to assume the editorship of the Chicago based CONSTRUCTOR. From 1934 to 1936, Winstead was the construction unit chief of the Division of Research and Planning, Industries Studies Section of the National Recovery Administration. Winstead subsequently became a field investigator for the U.S. Senate Civil Liberties Committee (La Follette Committee), 1936-1940; a field examiner for the National Labor Relations Board, 1940-1942; and a national representative of the Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America. His last professional effort was as an investigator of the attempted assassination of Walter Reuther in 1948.
Scope and Contents
National Recovery Administration (NRA) documents in this collection largely relate to the construction industry and include carbons of preliminary and summary reports (1933-1935) on the industry and NRA codes; manuscript documents on sources of then current statistics on construction, on the status of the American Federation of Labor unions functioning in the industryk, and on building trades wages in a variety of cities from 1925 to 1935. Also a memorandum from Winstead to James E. Hughes regarding the revision or elimination of construction codes.
U.S. Senate Civil Liberties Committee (La Follette Committee) documents include carbon copies of reports by Winstead and other field investigators dealing with alleged anti-union espionage activities, largely in Texas, engaged in by the following: Sugarland Industries, the Texas Can Company, the Freeport Sulphur Company, the Marshall Canning Company, the Weirton Steel Company, the Ford Motor Company, International Corporation Services, the Corporation Auxiliary Company, and the Waeker Brothers Iron Company. Victims of this alleged spying campaign included the National Maritime Union, the Industrial Workers of the World, the Oil Workers' International Union, the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, the Steelworkers Organization Committee, the Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel and Tin Workers, the United Mine Workers of America, and the United Retail and Wholesale Employees. Included with the reports are notes, letters, and financial documents. Significant correspondence includes that of J. Edgar Hoover, Robert M. La Follette Jr., Malcolm Halliday (assistant general counsel) and Heber Blankenhorn. A major subject of the reports was the activities of the Corporation Auxiliary Company.
National Labor Relations Board documents include papers concerning the 1949 staff hearing examiners controversy. These consist of manuscript documents ranking prospective candidates for the position of hearing examiner, petitions regarding the Civil Service Commission's attempt to remove hearing examiners, and reports, memoranda, briefs, and letters regarding the controversy. Charles Antone Horsky (lawyer) is the chief correspondent.
Documents relating to the Shipbuilders Stabilization Committee include dockets of interpretive rulings regarding work rules, wages, fringe benefits and apprentice training; and various documents having to do with zone standards in the industry.
Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America (IUMSWA) documents include constitutions, by-laws, agreements, minutes, publications, reports and correspondence. Of special interest are the materials on the 1945 dispute of the union with the Todd Shipbuilding Corporation and the Bethlehem Steel Corporation (San Pedro yard). Also included are documents (1941-1942) regarding the IUMSWA organizing activities, including briefs on hiring, employment and communist activities; memos on jurisdictional disputes between the American Federation of Labor and the Congress of Industrial Organizations, and proposed union policy for shipyard hiring practices in Washington and Oregon. Major correspondents include John Green (president, IUMSWA) and George Smith (a national representative).
Also, a lengthy exchange of correspondence (1922, 1943-1944) between Winstead and Walter N. Polakov (industrial diagnostician and engineering counselor) largely concerning the direct and indirect costs of mine accidents; manuscripts and publications of Winstead on the history of union busting, a history of the construction industry (1920-1934), a history of the IUMSWA, a pamphlet on legal right for ship-building workers and a "union busters and finks" handbook.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 24, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 13, 2019
Construction workers; Examiners (Administrative procedure) -- United States; Labor unions and communism -- United States; Shipbuilding industry -- Employees; Shipbuilding industry -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Labor unions -- Jurisdictional disputes -- United States; Wages -- Shipbuilding industry -- United States; Blankenhorn, Heber, 1884-1956.; Blood, Ross P.; Halliday, Malcolm.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Horsky, Charles Antone.; La Follette, Robert M. (Robert Marion), 1895-1953.; Polakov, Walter (Walter Nicholas), b. 1879.; Winstead, Ralph D. (Ralph Dimmit), 1894-1949.; Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel and Tin Workers of North America; American Federation of Labor; Bethlehem Steel Corporation; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Corporation Auxiliary Company; Ford Motor Company; Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America; Industrial Workers of the World; International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers, and Helpers; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America; National Corporation Services; National Maritime Union of America; Oil Workers' International Union; Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union; Steel Workers Organizing Committee (U.S.); Texas Can Company; United Mine Workers of America; United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on Education and Labor. Subcommittee on Civil Liberties; United States. National Labor Relations Board; United States. National Recovery Administration; United States. Shipbuilders Stabilization Committee
3833925
- Material Bearing on the Painting, Wallpapering and Decorating Division of the Construction Industry, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  October 21 1933
- National Recovery Administration, Division of Economic Research and Planning, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  March 21 1934
- Plumbing Contractors Division of the Construction Industry, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  March - April 1934
- Insulating Contractors Division of the Construction Industry, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  April 25 1934
- Plastering and Lathing Contractors Divisions of the Construction Industry, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Heating, Piping and Air Conditioning Contractors Division of the Construction Industry, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  May 12 1934
- Pipe Line Construction Division of the Construction Industry, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  June 21 1934
- Architect's Division of the Construction Industry, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  July 3 1934
- Building Contractors' Subdivision of the General Contractor's Division of the Construction Industry, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  August 10 1934
- Sub divisional Code for Highway Contractors, Chapter II-C of the General Contractor's Code, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  September 7 1934
- Sub divisional Code for Heavy Construction and Railroad Contractors' Chapter II-B of the General Contractors' Code, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  October 1 1934
- National Recovery Administration Division of Review. The Evidence Study Series No. 7. The Construction Industry., 1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  June 1935
- National Recovery Administration. Research and Planning Division. Code Administration Study. Preliminary Report on Construction Industry., 1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Preliminary Report on the Construction Industry and NRA Codes. Volume 1., 1935 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  December 17 1935
- The Construction Industry and NRA Construction Codes. Volume 1., 1935 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- The Construction Industry and NRA Construction Codes. Volume 2. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Summary Report on the Construction Industry and NRA Construction Codes., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  March 18 1936
- Construction Industry and NRA Construction Codes. Miscellaneous., 1935 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  March 12 1935
- National Labor Relations Board. Hearings by Winstead. Data Sheets., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- US Civil Service Commission. Trial Examiners of the NLRB., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Removal of Trial Examiners and Anti-Strike Legislation, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Lawyer-Manufacturer Plot to Overtake Federal Agencies. Newspaper Clippings., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- NAM-ABA Control of Federal Agencies. Newspaper Clippings., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Civil Services Commission Resigns. Newspaper Clippings., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Identification of PFW Operative by FBI, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Identification of Further Operatives, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Operatives and Espionage in Texas, 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Ford Motor Company. Dallas-NLRB Case Z-809. Original., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Labor Espionage and Dynamiting in Texas, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Anti-Labor Activity in Texas, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Corporation Auxiliary Company Investigation., 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Corporation Auxiliary Co. Investigation., 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Corporation Auxiliary Co. and the Texas Co., 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- G-373 Reports for the Texas Co., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Further Investigations into Operatives, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Testimony of A. Chester Brazier in the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Anti-Union Activities in West Virginia., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- N-338 Reports and Expenses., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- O-377 Reports and Expenses., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- G-373 and N-291 Reports and Expenses, 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Further Investigations., 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Contains 3 pads of paper
- Investigation into JC Boyer et al, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Local 9, Industrial Union of Shipbuilding and Marine Workers of America, CIO, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Shipbuilders of America, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Contains 6 drawings
- Local No. 9. Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America., 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Dispute by Local No. 9 and the National War Labor Board, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Constitutions and By-Laws of the IUMSWA, 1940-1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Bethlehem Steel Co. and the Shipbuilding Workers of America, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Todd Shipbuilding Corporation and the IUMSWA, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- IUMSWA Basic Agreement for Small Shops, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Shipbuilding Workers of America Miscellaneous, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Taft-Hartley Bill Summary. Shipbuilding Workers of America., 1947 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Work by Winstead for Locals No. 9 and 52 of the IUMSWA., 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Shipbuilding Stabilization Committee. Documents. Washington, DC., 1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  December 12 1946.
- Shipbuilding Stabilization Committee. Zone Standards and Agreements., 1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Washington, DC.
- Interpretive Rulings. Shipbuilding Stabilization Committee. Dockets., 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Shipbuilding Stabilization Committee. Documents and Notes. Washington, DC., 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Shipbuilding Stabilization Committee. Documents. "History of the American Labor Movement"., 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Shipbuilding Stabilization Committee. Documents and Memos. Washington, DC., 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Shipbuilding Stabilization Committee and the Pacific Coast Shipbuilding Zone Conference., 1942-1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Peoples Educational Association. Minutes and Booklets., 1945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- "Union Busters Inc.". Edited Manuscript by Ralph D Winstead., 1937 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Labor Newspaper Clippings Written by Ralph Winstead., 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Edited Manuscript Pages. Untitled. Ralph Winstead. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  No Date
- "Chronological History of the Construction Industry 1920-1934" and "The Song of Mark McKee"., 1935 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Status of Unions in the Construction Field. Data Tables. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  No date.
- Correspondence with and Writing of Walter N. Polakov, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Sources and Methods of Collecting Construction Data. Political Cartoons. "Victory through Unionism" Booklet. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Further Chapters in a Book on Labor History. Pages 58-93. Untitled. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Large Table of Construction Industry Wages by City, 1925., 1935 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  November 1 1935
- "Contraction Industry: NIR Act, Construction Code, Supplements, Amendments". RD Winstead., 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Timeline of Labor History Movement Written out on Notecards. Source Material for Book. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  No date
- The Constructor R.D. Winstead, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- The Constructor R.D. Winstead, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- The Constructor R.D. Winstead, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- The Constructor R.D Winstead, 1932-1934 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Award from Stuart Junior High school for Olga Winstead, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Construction Pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 9)
- History of the American Labor Movement (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Ralph Correspondence M-V (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Ralph Correspondence A-L (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Ralph Winstead Correspondence, 1950-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Ralph Winstead Employment, 1927-1948 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Letters to Olga Peters (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Handwritten Notes from Ralph Winstead (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Ralph Winstead (Box 4, Folder 1)